A Guide to the William A. Duerr Papers, 1934-1987
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
William A. Duerr Papers, 1934-1987
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1975-006
1.0 cu. ft. 2 boxes
Extracts, reprints and typescripts of scientific reports on forestry, authored or co-authored by William A. Duerr, professor of Forestry at Virginia Tech, 1972-1980.
Duerr, William A.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The William A. Duerr Papers were donated to Special Collections in several accruals, beginning in 1975 and ending in 1990.
Biographical Note
William A. Duerr was born in Maine on July 7, 1911. By 1930, he was living in Manhattan with his widowed mother, Virginia R. Duerr. Duerr graduated from Iowa State College before obtaining a master's degree in agricultural economics (University of Minnesota) and a Ph.D. in economics from Harvard in 1944. He served in the research branch of the U. S. Forest Service for several years and was in charge of forest surveys and economics research at the Southern Forest Experiment Station in New Orleans for six years following World War II. Duerr served as chairman of the Forestry Economics Department at the New York State College of Forestry from 1952 until 1972, when he was hired to fill Virginia Tech's Thomas M. Brooks professorship in forestry. He served in that position until 1980. William A. Duerr died on December 25, 2002.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains writings of William A. Duerr, professor of forestry at Virginia Tech from 1972 to 1980. Included are extracts and reprints of articles for various scholarly journals, books, and professional conferences, as well as working copies of two books. The publications were all authored or co-authored by Duerr and relate to various topics in foestry.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged according to numbers assigned, apparently, at the time of accessioning. A few items which had no pre-assigned numbers were numbered at the time of processing and placed at the end of the collection. The arrangement generally follows a rough chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
Several publications were separated from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection. These items may be accessed through a search of the library's catalog.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Faculty; Forests and forestry; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Publications 1-5 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - The Ames Forester. Ames, IA: Iowa State College Forestry Club, 1934
  - "A Yield Table for Northern Hardwoods in the Lake States." Journal of Forestry 35.4: 340-343, Apr 1937
  - "Comments on the General Application of Gehrhardt's Formula for Approach Toward Normality." Journal of Forestry 36.6: 600-604, Jun 1938
  - "Growth Prediction and Site Determination in Uneven-Aged Timber Stands." Journal of Agricultural Research 56.2: 81-98, Jan 15 1938
  - "Methods of Predicting Growth of Forest Stands." Economic Notes (Lake States Forest Experiment Station) 9, Apr 1938
- Publications 6-8 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - "Results of a Commercial Selective Cutting in Northern Hemlock-Hardwoods." Journal of Forestry 36.12: 1224-1230, Dec 1938
  - Volume and Yield of Northern White Cedar in the Lake States. St. Paul, MN: Lake State Forest Experiment Station, 1939
  - "Farm Forestry in the Lake States: an Economic Problem." Circular (United States Department of Agriculture) 661, Nov 1942
- Publication 9 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - "The Forest Situation in Piedmont Virginia." Forest Survey Release (Appalachian Forest Experiment Station) 13, May 15 1943
- Publications 10-17 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - "Appalachian Forests: Full and Better Use." Land Policy Review 7.1: 16-21, Spring 1944
  - "A Postwar Program for Forestry in the Appalachian Region." Journal of Forestry 44.2: 100-107, Feb 1946
  - "Timber-Products Marketing in Eastern Kentucky." Bulletin (Kentucky Agricultural Experiment Station) 488, Jun 1946
  - "Timber Resources of the Lower South, 1946." Forest Survey Release (Southern Forest Experiment Station) 55, May 20 1946
  - "Timber Resources of the Lower South, 1946." Southern Pulp and Paper Journal 9.9: 58-59, 64, Sep 15 1946
  - "Farms and Forests of Eastern Kentucky in Relation to Population and Income." Bulletin (Kentucky Agricultural Experiment Station) 507, Aug 1947
  - "The New Southern Forest Survey" typescript, 1947
  - "Research in the Economics of Forestry." Ames Forester 32-35: 11-23, 1947
- Publications 18-26 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - "Farm Management." Journal of Forestry 46.1: 57-58, Jan 1948
  - "Forest Survey of Arkansas Ozarks Completed" typescript, 1948
  - "Management of Forests in an Eastern Kentucky Area." Bulletin (Kentucky Agricultural Experiment Station) 518, May 1948
  - "The Small, Low-Income Landholding: a Problem in Forest Conservation." Iowa State College Journal of Science 22.4: 449-460, Jul 1948
  - "Toward Defining the Economics of Forestry." Proceedings Society of American Foresters Meeting 1947: 94-99, 1948
  - "The Forest Economics Scope and Method Project: Progress and Problems." Proceedings Society of American Foresters Annual Meeting, 1948
  - "A Guide to Profitable Tree Utilization." Occasional Paper (Southern Forest Experiment Station) 114, Nov 1949
  - "Mississippi Forest Area Increases but Timber Quality Declines." Mississippi Farm Research 12.11: 8, Nov 1949
  - "Mississippi's Timber Resources" typescript, 1949
- Publications 27-40 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - "The New Forest Survey of Mississippi." Southern Lumberman 179.2245: 54-55, 58, 62, Oct 15 1949
  - "Pine and Hardwood Trends in the Lower South" typescript, 1949
  - "Research in the Economics of Forestry, 1940-1947." Journal of Forestry 47.4: 265-270, Apr 1949
  - "The Southern Hardwood Problem." Southern Lumberman 179.2249: 147-152, Dec 15 1949
  - "Guides to Profitable Forest Management." Proceedings Association of Southern Agricultural Workers, Biloxi Mississippi 92, 1950
  - "Guides to Profitable Forest Management." Journal of Forestry 49.11: 771-773, Nov 1951
  - "Private Forest Management in the Lower South." Ames Forester 37: 32-46, 1950
  - "Second Forest Survey of Southwest Arkansas" typescript, 1950
  - "Tree Distribution in Mississippi." Forest Survey Release (Southern Forest Experiment Station) 64, Jun 1950
  - "Guides to Profitable Forest Management." Forest Farmer 10.11: 8, 15, 1951
  - "The South's Income from Timber Products." Forest Farmer 10.6: 5, 1951
  - "Undergraduate Forest Economics: Its Function and Content" typescript, 1951
  - "The Forest Future of the South." Journal of Forestry 50.3: 179-181, Mar 1952
  - "Optimum Stocking of a Selection Forest." Journal of Forestry 50.1: 12-16, Jan 1952
- Publications 41-51 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - "Private Forest Management in the American 'Lower South.'" Unasylva 6.2: 59-65, Jun 1952
  - "Private Forest Management in the Lower South." Alabama Conservationist 24.4: 14-15, 32-33, 35, Jan 1953
  - "Private Forest Management in the Lower South." Alabama Conservationist 24.5: 22-23, 27-28, Apr 1953
  - "A Standard Hardwood Quality Index: Proceedings of a Symposium." Journal of Forestry 51.11: 830-831, Nov 1953
  - "Technological Progress, Master Key to New England's Forestry Future." Monthly Review, Federal Reserve Bank of Boston 35.5: 5-6, May 1953
  - "Technology--Key to Forest Abundance." Northeastern Logger 1.12: 12-13, Aug 1953
  - "Pulpwood vs. Sawlog Rotations." APA 1954 Pulpwood Annual, 24, 26, 1954
  - "Some Research Needs in the Economics of Forestry." Proceedings Society of American Foresters Meeting 1954: 161-162, 1955
  - "Financial Maturity: a Guide to Profitable Timber Growing." Technical Bulletin (United States Department of Agriculture), Aug 1956
  - "Let's Not Divorce Economics and Policy." Journal of Forestry 55.9: 671-672, Sep 1957
  - "Forest Taxation Problems--How Serious and for Whom?" Proceedings Society of American Foresters 1957: 125-128, 1958
  - "Program Summary." New York Forester 15.3: 4-5, Aug 1958
- Publications 52-66 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - "The Economics of Forestry, Introduction." Economics for Agriculture. Cambridge, MA: Harvard UP, 1959
  - "Teaching Forestry Economics." Iowa State Journal of Science 34.4: 507-512, May 15 1960
  - "The Future Demand for Wood." The Challenges of Forestry. Syracuse, NY: State University College of Forestry, 1961
  - "The Future for Wood-Using Industry in New York State." Journal of Forestry 59.11: 821-824, Nov 1961
  - "The Role of Economics in Forestry Progress." Forestry Chronicle 37.2: 116-122, Jun 1961
  - "Some Interesting Research in Forestry Economics." New York Forester 18.4: 15-18, Nov 1961
  - "Economic Guides to Multiple-Use Policy." Proceedings Society of American Foresters Meeting 1963: 163-166, 1964
  - Rev. of A Place to Live: the Yearbook of Agriculture, 1963. Journal of Forestry: 276, Apr 1964
  - "Forestry as a System." New York Forester 23.2: 2-4, May 1965
  - "The Allowable Cut of Timber: Policy Issues and Alternatives." Proceedings Society of American Foresters Meeting: 95-99, 1966
  - Rev. of Systems of Forest Taxation and Tax Impact Upon Private Forestry in Several European Countries by Werner Kroth. Journal of Forestry 64.11: 758, Nov 1966
  - "The Changing Shape of Forest Resource Management." Journal of Forestry 65.8: 526-529, Aug 1967
  - "Forest Resource Management: Some Decision Theory and Illustrations." Chance and Change, a Seminar on Decision Theory. Vancouver: University of British Columbia, 1967
  - "Conversion Surplus as a Measure of Value." The Forestry Chronicle 44.4: 24-27, Aug 1968
- Publications 67-72 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - "Decision Making in Forest Resource Management." Journal of Forestry: 760-763, Oct 1968
  - "Testimony Concerning the Allowable Cut of Timber." State of Oregon, Fifty-fourth Legislative Assembly, Public Lands Interim Committee: 1-12, Jun 15 1968
  - "The Long Trend in Wood Use." Forest Engineering Conference Proceedings, Kellogg Center, Michigan State University, East Lansing. St. Joseph, MI: American Society of Agricultural Engineers, 1969
  - "What Is Happening to the Forestry Profession?" Journal of Forestry 67.6: 379-382, Jun 1969
  - "The Problem of Varied Goals in Forestry." Proceedings of Sixth World Forestry Congress, Madrid, June 1966: 3940-3944, 1970
  - "Guides to Land Management, an Integrated Operations-Research Project with a Systems Viewpoint." Bulletin (British Forestry Commision) 44: 72-78, 1971
- Publication 73 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - "Research Needs and Priorities for BLM Forestry in Western Oregon" [draft]. Portland, OR: U. S. Bureau of Land Management, 1971
- Publications 74-79 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - "The Role of Faith in Forest Resource Managment." Man and the Ecosystem. Burlington, VT: Queen City Printers, 1971
  - "The Heredity and Environment of Professional Forestry Eduction" typescript, 1971
  - "Professional Forestry Employment: the Context and the Issues." Journal of Forestry 71.8: 491-493, Aug 1973
  - "Goals, Prospects, Problems." American Journal of Agricultural Economics 56.5: 927-935, Dec 1974
  - "Guides to Land Management--a Research and Development Project: Purpose, Procedure, History, Afterthoughts, 1964-1974." Guides to Land Management Report 21, Feb 1975
  - "Allowable Timber Cuts on Federal Lands in Oregon: a Tempest in a Teapot." Congressional Record: 374-387, Jan 17 1966
- Publications 80-81 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - "Some Financial Optima for Timber." Scandinavian Forest Economics 18: 3-7, May 1978
  - "Social Sciences in Forestry as a Field of Research: What Is the Forest Service Doing, and How Well?" 1980
- Publication 82 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Forest Resource Management: Decision-Making Principles and Cases. Corvallis, OR: O.S.U. Book Stores, 1974
- Publication 83 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Forest Resource Management: Decision-Making Principles and Cases. Corvallis, OR: O.S.U. Book Stores, 1975, [2 folders]
- Publications 84-[89] (Box-folder 2-4)
  - "Some Economics of Forestry Practice Controls." Proceedings Seventh Annual Forestry and Wildlife Forum: 73-81, 1976
  - "Our Exciting Future." Ames Forester 66: 30-31, 1979
  - Rev. of The Microeconomics of the Timber Industry by David H. Jackson. Journal of Forestry: 79.1: 40, Jan 1981
  - "Forestry Excellence in the 1980s." The 1984 Ames Forester: 7, 20, 1984
  - "Forestry's Upheaval: Are Advances in Western Civilization Redefining the Profession?" Journal of Forestry 84.1: 20-26, Jan 1986
  - "Eastern Hardwood Managment: Some Economic Background." Penn State Forest Resource Issues Conference, University Park, PA, March 9-11, 1987: 1-9, [1987]
  - Rev. of Natural Resources: Bureaucratic Myths and Environmental Managment by Richard L. Stroup and John A. Baden. Journal of Forestry: 114, Feb 1984